this is my response to the podcast or
video on rebel wisdom called the war on
sense-making
by daniel Mettenberger i loved this this
podcast that i listened to a walking
talks all about sense making and how the
difference in truth and and truthfulness
and all the link language that i'm not
gonna do right because language is not
my strong strong point that it's one of
the biggest challenges for my brain but
this is the idea that I've tackled and
this is what the the technological
cooperative helps us tackle because we
don't need to have things make sense to
everybody
what we need to do is develop a way for
people who want the sense making who
want to understand the complex problems
and be able to talk to other people who
understand the complex problems to
understand the complexity and just like
you talks about in there and I've talked
about one human brain can't retain all
of the knowledge and yet it is all
somewhat contained on online but it's
not accessible it's not what do we trust
and if it's not if we we can't learn
from it directly and even if we could
even if we had a genius brain where
they're not conversing with people who
understand that knowledge so we need a
way to have trust for the information
which involves having a conversation
before even ever tackling whether this
thing is trustworthy we have to remove
our bias by having the conversation
beforehand before we have a debate on
whether the scientific paper follows our
worldview or not we need to have the
discussion of like what algorithm would
grade this science so that we can know
how trustworthy the science is was it
repeatable how many people were in this
study what were the rigorous and
rigorous um like have an actual
discussion about every scientific paper
everyone's not going to have that
conversation but people who want to have
that conversation making it accessible
to them as possible having layers of
information so data the raw data
available as much as we can to everybody
then no one's gonna actually look at
that very few people are gonna look at
that but
you could look at it then having a layer
on top of it of the peer review and the
actual journal like the articles that
are written on that information having
people all the way up to and he does not
agree with us having it understandable
by the masses having it explainable to
an eighth grade or having explainable to
a fourth grader how many explainable to
a five-year-old because if we want
people to understand blockchain if we
want people to understand climate change
we look at the whole picture of it and
the people who can make the intellectual
deep conversation or having that but we
also needed it at a level that is
understandable and people to play with
the data together we need to develop the
system where we trust it it doesn't
matter it doesn't need 7.5 billion
people to trust it doesn't even need our
politicians and our corporations to
trust it because they're not going to as
he talks about for the entire podcast
which is an hour in 50 minutes long
they're all ready in order to make
profit they're already biased against
craving that we can't trust our
governments they used to be we could
trust our government websites and now we
no longer can we can create we can have
once they open source that's not right
like to libraries but he talks about a
Geiger counter and everyone has a Geiger
counter and everyone has a microscope
and everyone has these tools to be able
to to publish data we can make that
accessible we can make it accessible
when we create the co-operative that has
that's the truth piece of our
cooperative is tackling this issue
having the conversation on how do we
trust science what do we trust in
economics and it's not about perfect
it's not about having it be perfect it's
about getting the best of and then
continually improving it there is a way
to have sense making we have to do it
together because if a tiny group of
people get together behind closed doors
and make sense of it they then have to
sell it back to us if everyone can be
involved as deeply as they want to be
and can be involved and if you want to
understand a subject it is made
available to you in your learning style
that is how we make sense of all of the
interlocking problems the only way to
make sense of it and then to be able to
be open to what is going wrong with what
we've done
what data do we need our own personal
data that again you have to be we have
to let people retain control of even if
it makes for less rigorous science
because the only way people are going to
feel comfortable giving their data for
the greater good is if they retain
control of it so I just wanted to come
on and say a little bit about that that
I know how we create sense making with
the global technical global tech
cooperative this is one of the things
people to be tackling is how do we in
every different area how do we know what
is true not perfectly true because there
generally isn't there's always gray area
but how do we tackle climate change
what's every question we would want to
know about vaccines and which ones have
actually been answered instead of just
looking at what was published
brainstorming before you ever get to
which side you're on
what would what we want to know in a
perfect world and what's hatch then
studied and what can be studied that
hasn't been studied and what has been
studied where does it fall and who
funded those studies we can make the
metadata ourselves we can organize the
metadata we can make the information
usable and understandable so that we can
move forward on creating actual
solutions and so that's just what I
wouldn't respond to this because I do
have some solutions just kind of cause
guess what he says like you shouldn't
think you have solutions I do I know I
have solutions to this since make heat
is what I am here to do on this planet
is help create it make sense because I
can't contain it all in my brain
no one can I can't even contain all of
what I went to the University for which
is ecology and genetics in my head I
want it visual I want to be able to play
with the information I want to be able
to tackle it with other people and not
have it inaccessible to people simply
because they don't have a degree or
they're not invited to that conference
we need to make it actually accessible
to the masses
bye see you tomorrow this is my second
video today my other one was live though
a better world is on its way please like
and subscribe hit that little bell we're
gonna create the technological
cooperative that makes all the sense
making and gives us an abundant and
happy life for every human being who
wants to participate in it take care